<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | heykieran Code Notes</title>
    <link>https://heykieran.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://heykieran.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Kieran J. Owens 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 11:10:38 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://heykieran.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://heykieran.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cadence Workflow and Clojure</title>
      <link>https://heykieran.github.io/post/cadence-and-clojure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 11:10:38 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://heykieran.github.io/post/cadence-and-clojure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    A repository with some working code and implementation notes can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/heykieran/cadence-test&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the occasion recently to investigate, and cursorily evaluate, a number of workflow
orchestration systems for use on a project with which I was involved. One of those systems,

&lt;a href=&#34;https://cadenceworkflow.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cadence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, particularly appealed to me - there was something very &lt;em&gt;Clojuresque&lt;/em&gt; about it;
certainly something very suggestive of a functional language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has the concept of state &lt;em&gt;durability&lt;/em&gt; (in workflow functions) that bears more than a passing
resemblance to the persistent data structures of Clojure - but extended across time. This
concept, similar to checkpoints, opens avenues to consistent, predictable restarts after
failures. If one can restore the complete state of a system to a known &lt;em&gt;good-state&lt;/em&gt; then one can
continue as if the failure had never occurred. Of course, if system-wide (or even better,
distributed) non-volatile RAM ever becomes a reality then Cadence would not be needed. This
strikes me as essence of the problem Cadence is attempting to solve, or, at least, the gap it&amp;rsquo;s
attempting to bridge. Cadence also allows, through activities, the use of non-persistent
data structures which can be considered as being analogous to the concept of a &lt;em&gt;side-effect&lt;/em&gt; in Clojure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The separation of the &lt;em&gt;functional&lt;/em&gt; from the &lt;em&gt;side-effect&lt;/em&gt;-ing, and the elision of
infrastructure and communication failure concerns leaves developers with simpler, almost always
more tractable, domain logic concerns and significantly reduces the cognitive load.
This is similar to the benefits often realized through the adoption of functional languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brief-tour-to-cadence&#34;&gt;A Brief Tour to Cadence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cadenceworkflow.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cadence&lt;/a&gt; is a workflow automation system developed by Uber. It shares many features
with other workflow automation systems but differs by being uniquely
&lt;em&gt;fault-oblivious&lt;/em&gt; rather than merely &lt;em&gt;fault-tolerant&lt;/em&gt;. The approach adopted by Cadence simplifies
greatly the work of developers who are relieved of many of the burdens of coordinating
activities and recovering from system or service failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cadence is complex but three concepts core to its understanding are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cadence Service itself,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow Workers and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activity Workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cadence service, backed by a persistent data-store such as Cassandra or MySql, is responsible for
orchestrating the activities of both type of workers, for maintaining history, and in the case of failure,
for recovering the state of all workflows (but not activities).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, the Cadence service instructs a Workflow Worker to execute a Workflow function. The Workflow function,
which implements business logic, is guaranteed by Cadence to be &lt;em&gt;durable&lt;/em&gt;. That is, its state, including its
thread stack and thread-local variables, are known and stored by Cadence, and in the case of failure
they are restored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workflows, like the business processes they typically model, may be long-running. It&amp;rsquo;s not unusual for a
real-world business process to take days or even months to complete, and Cadence provides excellent facilities
to support such long-running processes within workflow functions. Therefore, the durability of the workflow functions (with the guaranteed
recovery of their states across failures) enables a simple &lt;em&gt;straight-line&lt;/em&gt; view of the business logic. This
greatly reduces the complexity of the development process by reducing the burden on the developer to anticipate
and mitigate &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; failure modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to guarantee durability across failures Cadence places a number of
restrictions on the code in Workflow functions. The code must be &lt;em&gt;deterministic&lt;/em&gt; i.e. executing the code
must produce the same result no matter how often it is run. Therefore, certain actions are forbidden within
workflow code - examples being: interacting &lt;strong&gt;directly&lt;/strong&gt; with external services, getting the time, getting random values,
and creating or suspending threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These type of actions are fundamentally non-deterministic and would make full recovery of the workflow state impossible.
However, the Cadence API provides alternatives for &lt;strong&gt;some&lt;/strong&gt; of these that produce deterministic behavior; and
which assure the recoverability of the function&amp;rsquo;s local variables, threads and state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For situations requiring interaction with external services (&lt;em&gt;the outside world&lt;/em&gt;), Cadence insists
that all communication be conducted through Activities, using Activity Workers. Activities do not share with Workflows
any of Cadence&amp;rsquo;s requirement that they be deterministic. Essentially anything is allowed in activities and any
clean-up after failure becomes the responsibility of the developer rather than the Cadence service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, &lt;em&gt;(but not precisely)&lt;/em&gt;, a Workflow Worker will start an Activity Worker (or multiple Activity Workers) to interact with the
outside world. Examples of an Activity might be interacting with a web-service, getting or saving a record to
a database, or awaiting human input, such as a decision. Cadence offers no guarantees about activity state,
and that state is not recovered in the case of failures of the Cadence infrastructure i.e. within the Cadence service itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to control a running workflow, or to affect its state, it can be signalled using events delivered by Cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cadence--clojure-challenges&#34;&gt;Cadence &amp;amp; Clojure Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signature of the worker registration function is &lt;code&gt;registerWorkflowImplementationTypes(java.lang.Class&amp;lt;?&amp;gt;... workflowImplementationClasses)&lt;/code&gt;
and in the documentation there is the note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for registration accepting workflow class, but not the workflow instance is that workflows are stateful and a new instance is created for each workflow execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s not noted, but implied, is that the constructor for the classes must have zero-arg constructors. This is problematic
for Clojure as instance variable declared in &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt; will create on constructor taking exactly that number of instance variables as
arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might then consider inheritance of the &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt;-d class to workaround the zero arg constructor issue
leaving a cleaner, more Clojure-esque result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, although &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt; can create a Java class with the fields you need, by default these fields are immutable;
but you could use &lt;code&gt;:volatile-mutable&lt;/code&gt; to allow the fields to be settable. Unfortunately, the bigger problem
is that the generated class is &lt;code&gt;public final&lt;/code&gt; which effectively eliminates the possibility that we
could use the class as a base class in &lt;code&gt;gen-class&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might have been helpful as we could define a zero-args constructor in &lt;code&gt;gen-class&lt;/code&gt; and then using the &lt;code&gt;:constructors&lt;/code&gt;
field map that constructor to the base class constructor and then assign default values to the field in the &lt;code&gt;:init&lt;/code&gt; method.
The fact that the &lt;code&gt;deftype&lt;/code&gt;-ed class is &lt;code&gt;final&lt;/code&gt; eliminates that approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-cadence--clojure-code&#34;&gt;Working Cadence &amp;amp; Clojure Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to fully investigate using Clojure with Cadence I developed a small set of demos to demonstrate how it works,
works around what doesn&amp;rsquo;t, and exercises the result. &lt;strong&gt;Very&lt;/strong&gt; little consideration was given to making the code more idiomatic,
at least from a Clojure perspective, or even particularly effective. I only making the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/heykieran/cadence-test&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;
available as it may prove helpful to others who would like to use Clojure with Cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repository also contains further notes on the implementation and lessons learnt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time allows I&amp;rsquo;ll probably return to the code, making it more idiomatic. But do let me know if you find it helpful, or share
your suggestions for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting-up Pedestal/Jetty with HTTPS</title>
      <link>https://heykieran.github.io/post/pedestal-jetty-https/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 13:39:37 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://heykieran.github.io/post/pedestal-jetty-https/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up Pedestal (using Jetty) with HTTPS isn&amp;rsquo;t that difficult, but
it is a bit &amp;ldquo;fiddly&amp;rdquo;. Essentially, you&amp;rsquo;ll need a keystore so that Jetty has
access to encryption keys and can encrypt pages sent over HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post only deals with self-signed certificates, but if you want to use
commercially-signed certificates it should work too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Just be aware that Jetty is happiest with the &lt;code&gt;pkcs12&lt;/code&gt; format - I&amp;rsquo;ve never got it to work satisfactorily
using other formats.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service Map (Pedestal)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to run Jetty under Pedestal you&amp;rsquo;ll need to supply a service map. The following service map works for me. You can change it as you need. The important elements in the
current context are where Jetty should look for the keystore (&lt;code&gt;keystore-location&lt;/code&gt;),
the &lt;code&gt;:ssl?&lt;/code&gt; key, the &lt;code&gt;:ssl-port&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;:security-provider&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Make sure the provider (Conscrypt) is in your &lt;code&gt;deps.edn&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(def service-map
  (let
    [keystore-location
     (if (System/getenv &amp;quot;KEYSTORE_LOCATION&amp;quot;)
       (-&amp;gt; (io/file (System/getenv &amp;quot;KEYSTORE_LOCATION&amp;quot;))
           (.getCanonicalPath))
       &amp;quot;/home/user/security/jetty-keystore&amp;quot;)]
    {::http/host &amp;quot;0.0.0.0&amp;quot;
     ::http/allowed-origins
                 {:allowed-origins (fn[_] true)
                  :creds true}
     ::http/routes #(deref #&#39;routes)
     ::http/type   :jetty
     ::http/container-options
     {:context-configurator jetty-websocket-configurator
      :h2c? true
      :h2 true
      :ssl? true
      :ssl-port 8081
      :keystore keystore-location
      :key-password &amp;quot;thepassword&amp;quot;
      :security-provider &amp;quot;Conscrypt&amp;quot;}
     ::http/port 8080}))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jetty Keystore&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order for Pedestal to start with Jetty,
it expects to find a keystore in a particular location
(see &lt;em&gt;Service Map&lt;/em&gt; notes above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the keystore (I&amp;rsquo;ve plagiarized/assembled from the following
pieces of information web, and I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I can&amp;rsquo;t remember the source(s).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generate a private site key (&lt;code&gt;site.key&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ openssl genrsa -des3 -out site.key 2048
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a copy of &lt;code&gt;site.key&lt;/code&gt; and strip the password, so that it can be auto-loaded&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cp site.key site.orig.key
$ openssl rsa -in site.orig.key -out site.key
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generate a self-signed signing request (&lt;code&gt;site.csr&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ openssl req -new -key site.key -out site.csr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generate a self-signed certificate (&lt;code&gt;sitex509.crt&lt;/code&gt; - in &lt;strong&gt;x509&lt;/strong&gt; format for loading into the keystore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ openssl req -new -x509 -key site.key -out sitex509.crt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combine the self-signed certificate (&lt;code&gt;sitex509.crt&lt;/code&gt;) and site key (&lt;code&gt;site.key&lt;/code&gt;) and
export it in &lt;strong&gt;pkcs12&lt;/strong&gt; format (&lt;code&gt;site.pkcs12&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ openssl pkcs12 -inkey site.key -in sitex509.crt -export -out site.pkcs12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rename the keystore (&lt;code&gt;site.pkcs12&lt;/code&gt;) to jetty-keystore&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and adjust the service-map to use it&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
